<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>preaction</title>
        <link>http://preaction.github.io/blog/tag/personal/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/tag/personal.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <description>Blog feed of preaction</description>
        <generator>Statocles 0.054</generator>
        <item>
            <title>Be It Resolved in 2015</title>
            <link>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2015/01/07/be-it-resolved-in-2015.html</link>
            <guid>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2015/01/07/be-it-resolved-in-2015.html</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[
                <p>This year, I resolve to:</p>

<h2>1) Blog more</h2>

<p>I&#39;ve got dozens of blog posts waiting to be published. Time to publish them.
I&#39;ve got dozens of ideas for blog posts waiting to be written.  Time to write
them. I&#39;ve got monthly column ideas. Time to implement them.</p>

<h2>2) Cook more, and blog about it</h2>

<p>Two birds with one stone! I need to try new things in food, no matter how
popular they are. I have trouble talking about things that interest me, because
I take criticism too personally, and I have an intense need to be liked and
praised.</p>

<h2>3) Make a video game</h2>

<p>Playing the new Soda Crush Saga game reminded me of why I want to create video
games. There is no substitute for actually building things. Ideas must be
tested. Implementing ideas leads to new ideas. Ideas are cheap.</p>

<h2>4) Open up</h2>

<p>(i.e. blog about personal things). I&#39;m back to my old, completely-closed-off
self. I stare at the ground when walking from place to place to avoid eye
contact with anyone. I don&#39;t share my feelings with anyone, especially when I&#39;m
upset. I bury everything, because I have this idea that nobody wants to hear
about the things I&#39;m upset about. It turns out, those people aren&#39;t my friends.
I was right about that.</p>

<h2>5) Exercise</h2>

<p>I haven&#39;t been to the gym I&#39;m paying for in 6 weeks. Time to fix that. Time to
make my dream of a lean 180 a reality.</p>

<p>Writing blog posts satisfies my desire to do one thing on Github every day.
Making a video game will also satisfy that condition.</p>

<p>To make this all happen, I need to do a little every day.</p>

                    <p><a href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/2015/01/07/be-it-resolved-in-2015.html#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>
                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="/blog/tag/personal/">personal</a>
                    <a href="/blog/tag/progress/">progress</a>
                </p>
            ]]></description>
            <pubDate>
                Wed, 07 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Freedom From Speech&#39;s Consequences</title>
            <link>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/freedom-from-speechs-consequences.html</link>
            <guid>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/freedom-from-speechs-consequences.html</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[
                <p><a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/blog/2014/04/03/brendan-eich-steps-down-as-mozilla-ceo/">What happened to Brendan Eich at Mozilla (resigning over community uproar for
his continued support of Prop
8)</a>
has now happened to one of Github&#39;s founders. <a href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2014/04/21/farewell-github-hello-immersive-computing.html">Tom Preston-Werner has resigned
due to community uproar over gender-based
harassment</a>.</p>

<p>Some are decrying this as an infringement on free speech. That people should be
do and say with impunity anything that is not illegal. That all people should
not criticize or judge anyone who is not doing something illegal, as though the
law is the only true measurement of good and evil.</p>

                    <p><a href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/2014/04/26/freedom-from-speechs-consequences.html#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>
                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="/blog/tag/personal/">personal</a>
                </p>
            ]]></description>
            <pubDate>
                Sat, 26 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>It Begins in Fear</title>
            <link>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2013/01/06/it-begins-in-fear.html</link>
            <guid>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2013/01/06/it-begins-in-fear.html</guid>
            <description><![CDATA[
                <p>A long time ago, I used to blog about my feelings.</p>

<p>Obviously, since I’m a dude, I’m not supposed to have feelings. At least, I am
not supposed to have the feelings I confessed to having. At least, I am not
supposed to have those feelings if I am in sound mind.</p>

<p>I still have those posts from Livejournal or from my personal sites. I don’t
look at them anymore, but they’re there if I ever want to retread the mental
pathways of memory.</p>

<p>A long time ago, I used to talk about my feelings.</p>

                    <p><a href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/2013/01/06/it-begins-in-fear.html#section-2">Continue reading...</a></p>
                <p>Tags:
                    <a href="/blog/tag/personal/">personal</a>
                </p>
            ]]></description>
            <pubDate>
                Sun, 06 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000
            </pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>

