<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>http://preaction.github.io/blog/tag/rants/index.html</id>
    <title>Doug Bell</title>
    <updated>2014-06-22T02:16:07Z</updated>
    <link rel="self" href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/tag/rants.atom"/>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/tag/rants/index.html"/>
    <generator version="0.013">Statocles</generator>
    <entry>
        <id>http://preaction.github.io/blog/2013/04/11/thoughts-while-changing-the-api-of-a-massive-framework.html</id>
        <title>Thoughts while changing the API of a massive framework...</title>
        <author><name>preaction</name></author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="http://preaction.github.io/blog/2013/04/11/thoughts-while-changing-the-api-of-a-massive-framework.html" />
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[
            <p>At the Bank we have a home-grown ETL framework that we've been using for quite
some time. We recently completed a total rewrite, but unfortunately we left out
a few changes. Had I gotten those changes in 5 months ago, I would have only
had to break the API of about 10 modules. Today, in order to make those
changes, I have to break the API of 122 modules.</p>

<p>What follows is an account of this ordeal, provided for entertainment value
only. There will be a future post that explains some of the things I did to
make this task surmountable.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Day 1</h2>

<ul>
<li>3:45pm - 122 modules left</li>
<li>4:31pm - 112 modules left - And then I remember there's another feature to
add that will require another migration of all these modules I will have to do.</li>
<li>4:52pm - 106 modules left -
<a href="https://metacpan.org/module/Test::Continuous">Test::Continuous</a> removes 3
steps for each module. Total time saved: HOLY FUCK THAT'S AWESOME</li>
<li>5:35pm - 97 modules left - Every commit message during this ordeal is another
love note to those who put off this migration five months ago, when there were
only 10 modules to migrate.</li>
<li>6:09pm - 94 modules left - New API to change: Create a role to do it for me!
+100 experience points!</li>
<li>6:15pm - 93 modules left - Why unpack the hash of args passed-in to the
method if the method you're calling takes exactly the same arguments? <code>my
$arg_name = $args{arg_name}; return $self-&gt;method( arg_name =&gt; $arg_name )</code>
should never happen!</li>
<li>6:37pm - 87 modules left - A thought: If the other team using this project
ultimately rejects this API change, I get to write my own brand-new ETL
framework from scratch! Temptation, thy name is Zoidberg.</li>
<li>6:51pm - 84 modules left - Found a bug in the new API! Finally something
interesting to do!</li>
<li>7:00pm - 80 modules left - Every time you copy/paste code in tests, God
inflicts another programmer with carpal tunnel. Please think of the
programmers.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Day 2</h2>

<ul>
<li>3:02pm - 80 modules left - Let's see if I remember all the macros I left in
vim over the weekend... Test::Continuous is still running, which is nice</li>
<li>3:18pm - 71 modules left - The end is in sight!</li>
<li>4:30pm - 52 modules left - Perhaps I was premature...</li>
<li>6:30pm - 41 modules left - Caught up putting out fires in other places.
Derail.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Day 3</h2>

<ul>
<li>1:35pm - 41 modules left - Another bug in the new API. Doing it this way is
certainly shaking out the bugs.</li>
<li>2:21pm - 20 modules left - Smooth sailing at last...</li>
<li>3:47pm - 0 modules left - AND THE CROWD GOES WILD!</li>
</ul>

<p>Total time elapsed: 3.25+3.5+2.25 = 9 hours. Not bad for 130 commits to migrate
122 modules.</p>

        ]]></content>
        <updated>2013-04-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
        <category term="ARRAY(0x7f8cb65a6f50)" />
    </entry>
</feed>

